Guide to the Jacqueline de Jong Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jacqueline de Jong papers
1955-1983
1961-1969
GEN MSS 832
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
16.68
(30 boxes) + 1 broadside
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, printed materials, subject files, photographs and other papers relating to the life and work of Jacqueline de Jong from 1955 to 1983, with the bulk of the materials dating from the 1960s. It offers rich documentation of the European avant-garde of the period thanks to de Jong's connections with the Internationale situationniste (I.S.), Gruppe SPUR, and the Danish situationists. In particular, the production of de Jong's magazine The Situationist Times is extensively documented through voluminous correspondence with co-editors, contributors, and publishers, as well as through production materials such as article submissions, original maquettes, and distribution lists.
Jong, Jacqueline de, 1939-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Jacqueline de Jong on the Edith and Richard French Fund and the Frederick W. Hilles Fund, 2011-2013.
Jacqueline de Jong
Jacqueline de Jong (1939-), is a Dutch artist. She was associated with the social, political, and artistic movements Internationale situationniste and Gruppe SPUR during the 1960s, and served as editor of The Situationist Times from 1962 to 1967.
De Jong was born in 1939 in Hengelo, Netherlands, to art collectors Hans and Alice de Jong. De Jong and her mother found refuge in Switzerland during World War II, after which they returned to the Netherlands. In 1958, De Jong obtained a position at the Stedelijk Museum, a contemporary arts institution located in Amsterdam. Her parents' collecting and her experience at the museum exposed her to current artistic movements, including the Internationale situationniste (I.S.), recently formed by French intellectual Guy Debord and Danish artist Asger Jorn. Jorn had also been a founding member of the earlier avant-garde movements CoBrA (1948-1951) and International Movement for an Imaginist Bauhaus (1955-1957). De Jong and Jorn first met in 1958, and were romantic partners through the 1960s. De Jong herself joined the I.S. in 1960 and participated to the movement's fourth conference in London in September of that year. Though one of few women in the movement's inner circle, she assumed the leadership of its Dutch section.
De Jong's time in the I.S. proved short lived, as Debord dismissed her in 1962, but her engagement with situationism continued. Now residing in Paris, France, she founded the English-language magazine The Situationist Times, which she designed, edited, printed, and distributed from 1962 to 1967. With her first solo show and her participation in a Gruppe SPUR exhibition, the year 1962 also marked the beginnings of de Jong's professional art career. Through the 1960s, she exhibited paintings, sculptures, and drawings largely in the Netherlands, Denmark, and France. Involved in the politics of the day, de Jong participated in the May 1968 protests, and printed posters in support of the students on strike. In 1970, after the end of her relationship with Jorn, de Jong moved back to Amsterdam with gallerist Hans Brinkman to pursue her painting career.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence, 1955-1976. II. The Situationist Times Records, 1962-1970. III. Writings, 1962-1983. IV. Subject Files, 1957-1979. V. Professional Papers and Personal Papers, 1962-1975.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, printed materials, subject files, photographs and other papers relating to the life and work of Jacqueline de Jong from 1955 to 1983, with the bulk of the materials dating from the 1960s. The production of de Jong's magazine The Situationist Times is extensively documented through voluminous correspondence with co-editors, contributors, and publishers, as well as through production materials such as article submissions, original maquettes and distribution lists.
The collection offers rich documentation of the European avant-garde of the period thanks to de Jong's connections with the Internationale situationniste (I.S.), Gruppe SPUR, and the Danish situationists. Correspondents include the artists and writers Noël Arnaud, Guy Atkins, Pol Bury, Guy Debord, Gordon Fazakerley, Asger Jorn, Dieter Kunzelmann, Jørgen Nash, and H. P. (Hans-Peter) Zimmer. De Jong's subject files include tracts, manifestos, and periodicals issued by I.S. and Gruppe SPUR, as well as manuscript notes from the 1961 Göteberg Conference and materials relating to early situationist exhibitions. Original writings by Asger Jorn and Guy Atkins are also present.
The papers also include correspondence with gallery owners and original artists' books created by de Jong that offer some documentation of her early artistic career beyond her involvement with situationist groups.
The Situationist Times
The Situationist Times was a periodical in six issues published in Europe between 1962 and 1967 that blended situationist theory, political commentary, conceptual art, and avant-garde aesthetics.
The movement Internationale situationniste (I.S.) emerged out of the Internationale lettriste and the International Movement for an Imaginist Bauhaus in 1957, largely under the leadership of Guy Debord. The ideas of the group were embodied in the French-language journal Internationale situationniste, but did not have an English-language outlet. Disagreeing with Debord over the expulsion of the German Gruppe SPUR from the I.S. and over the role of visual arts in situationism, de Jong began publishing The Situationist Times shortly after he excluded her from the group.
Article contributions for the magazine came from practitioners of a range of disciplines active across Europe. With de Jong's original drawings, collages, and selections of photographic reproductions, the magazine's visual content reflected her artistic vision. The first issue, co-edited with French author Noël Arnaud, was released in May 1962 and focused heavily on Gruppe SPUR. De Jong, Arnaud, and Danish-Belgian artist Serge Vandercam co-edited the second issue, which was published in September 1962. The third issue, dated January 1963, was edited and published solely by de Jong, and printed in her home town of Hengelo, Netherlands. Articulated around the themes of knots, interlaces, and topology, it was the first in a thematic series. The subsequent issues were published and distributed by the Danish publishing company Rhodos. No. 4, released in October 1963, was the "labyrinths" issue, and no. 5, released in December 1964, was the "rings and chains" issue. Both were created in collaboration with English-born artist Gordon Fazakerley. Released in 1967, no. 6, the last published issue, exclusively contained original lithographs from 32 artists. De Jong planned a seventh issue on the theme of "wheels", but never completed it.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Box 31: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Art, Modern -- 20th Century -- Periodicals; Avant-garde (Aesthetics) -- Europe -- Periodicals; Conceptual art -- Periodicals; Counterculture -- Europe -- Periodicals; Literature, Experimental -- Europe -- 20th Century; Artists' books (books) -- Europe -- 20th Century; Photographs; Protest literature -- France -- Paris -- 20th Century; Situationist literature -- France -- Paris -- 20th Century; Periodical editors -- France -- Paris -- 20th Century; Situationism -- France -- Periodicals; Arnaud, Noël, 1919-2003; Atkins, Guy; Bucaille, Max, 1906-; Bury, Pol, 1922-2005; Debord, Guy, 1931-1994; Fazakerley, Gordon, 1937-2011; Jong, Jacqueline de, 1939-; Jorn, Asger, 1914-1973; Kunzelmann, Dieter, 1939-1998; Nash, Jørgen, 1920-2004; Zimmer, H. P., 1936-; Gruppe SPUR; Internationale situationniste
- Correspondence, 1955–1976; Series I; 4.8; (12 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence contains incoming and outgoing letters documenting de Jong's creative work and personal life from the late 1950s to the mid-1970s. De Jong's correspondence includes substantial discussions of the creation and distribution of The Situationist Times that complement the production materials found in Series II. The Situationist Times Records.
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: General Correspondence, and Family Correspondence.
  - General Correspondence, 1959–1976; 3.96; (10 boxes)
    General correspondence offers rich documentation of de Jong's artistic, professional, and personal networks, with a particular emphasis on the making of The Situationist Times. Correspondents include visual artists, writers, architects, gallery owners, printers, publishers, and friends residing across Europe, in addition to a handful of correspondents based in the Americas. Reflecting de Jong's transnational network, the correspondence is in Dutch, English, French, German, and Danish, in addition to a few letters in Norwegian and Italian.
    Correspondence with contributors to The Situationist Times illustrates de Jong's editorial process and places the magazine within a broader context of situationist and avant-garde thinking. Represented are co-editors Noël Arnaud, Serge Vandercam, and Gordon Fazakerley, as well as most of the artists, writers, and theorists who wrote pieces published by de Jong, such as Danish artist Asger Jorn, Belgian sculptor Pol Bury, French surrealist artist Max Bucaille, Belgian artist Pierre Alechinsky, Berlin-based intellectual Rodolphe Gasché, French architect and engineer David Georges Emmerich, and Dutch theoretical mathematician H. C. Doets. Due the romantic relationships de Jong forged with Asger Jorn and Pol Bury, correspondence with them is particularly voluminous and covers both professional and personal topics. Also of note is the voluminous correspondence between de Jong and employees of the Danish publishing company Rhodos, especially Erik Johannesen and Niels Blaedel, who acted as publisher and distributor of issues no. 4-6. The letters trace the friendship, working relationship, and financial disputes between Rhodos and de Jong.
    Correspondence with the founding figure of the Situationniste Internationale Guy Debord, with Danish leaders of the Second Situationist International Jørgen Nash and Jens Jørgen Thorsen, and with German members of Gruppe SPUR Lothar Fischer, Dieter Kunzelmann, H. P. (Hans Peter) Zimmer, and Heimrad Prem, provides further context for Jong's work with The Situationist Times, and highlights the intersections and disagreements between several contemporary avant-garde groups.
    Finally, the subseries also comprises correspondence from the 1960s with gallery owners, largely based in Northern Europe, regarding exhibitions of de Jong's artwork in the initial years of her artistic career. Also represented are collectors, like Hanns Sohm and Jon Nicholas Streep, and museum curators seeking to acquire copies of the magazine or other artwork, as well as other artists and architects in de Jong's professional network that were not associated with situationism.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Box 31: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
    - "A" general, 1960–1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Aberbach, Joachim Jean, 1961–1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Alechinsky, Pierre, 1964–1970 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Andersen, Knut, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Incoming and outgoing correspondence regarding an exhibition at the Oslo kunstforening (Oslo Art Society).
    - Arnaud, Noël, 1961–1969 (Box 1, Folder 6-11)
      Incoming letters, with some outgoing letters, from de Jong's co-editor, the bulk dating from 1962 and discussing the preparation of the magazine.
    - Atkins, Guy, 1961–1976 (Box 1, Folder 12-16)
      Incoming letters, with some outgoing letters, from the professor at the London School of Oriental and African Studies and friend of Asger Jorn, discussing Jorn and The Situationist Times.
      - Restricted fragile clipping, 1968 (Box 31, Folder 514)
    - "B" general, 1962–1976 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    - Balthazar, André, 1966–1976 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
      Incoming and outgoing correspondence with the Belgian poet and editor at Centre Daily-Bul & co., that also includes a transcript of his poem "Pleins tubes."
      Related Materials
      See also: Centre Daily-Bul & co., Box 2, folder 48.
    - Beck, Heinz, 1965–1968 (Box 1, Folder 21-23)
    - Berni, Antonio, 1968–1970 (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
    - Bhalotra, Ashok, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Biasi, Guido, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - [Bissen?], Charles V., 1968–1969 (Box 1, Folder 27a)
    - Böckelmann, Frank, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Incoming letters from the writer associated with Gruppe SPUR.
    - Boer, Lodewijk de, 1961–1963 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Boltanski, Christian, 1965–1970 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Borgens forlag / Jarl Borgen, 1964–1965 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Bucaille, Max, 1963–1966 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Bury, Pol, 1965–1976 (Box 2, Folder 33-45)
      Incoming letters, with one outgoing letter, from the Belgian sculptor, The Situationist Times contributor, and de Jong's romantic partner. Letters document their relationship and Bury's artistic activities and daily life, including his stay in New York City from 1966 to 1968, and are accompanied by clippings and notes. The bulk of the letters date from 1965 to 1966.
      See also: See also: Centre daily-Bul & co., Box 2, folder 48
      - Restricted fragile clippings, 1966-1967 (Box 31, Folder 515)
    - "C" general, 1960–1971 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Carl Petersens Enke A/S, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      Incoming reminders of accounts for binding The Situationist Times.
    - Centre Daily-Bul & co, 1965–1968 (Box 2, Folder 48)
      Small original grouping of letters from André Balthazar, Pol Bury, and Marianne [?], accompanied by fliers about Le Daily-Bul magazine. Located in La Louvière, Belgium, Centre Daily-Bul & co was founded in 1957 by Bury and Balthazar.
      See also: Balthazar, André, Box 1, folders 19-20; and Bury, Pol, Box 1, folders 33-45
    - Chapon Heule, Hetty, 1961–1969 (Box 2, Folder 49-54)
    - Claus, Jürgen, 1964–1965 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Crédit lyonnais, 1968–1969 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Cremer, Jan, 1961–1964 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - "D" general, 1965–1966 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Daché, Lilly, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 59)
      Outgoing letters regarding the planning of de Jong's 1967 exhibition at Galerie Lily Daché (New York).
    - Dalewijk, H. J., 1963–1970 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Debord, Guy, 1960–1964 (Box 3, Folder 61-62)
      Incoming and outgoing letters from 1960-1962 regarding the Internationale situationniste, Gruppe SPUR, and the fourth situationist conference in London. Accompanied by a copy of a 1964 letter from Luc de Heusch to Pierre Alechinsky.
      See also: Series IV. Subject Files, "Dossier ICA, London 1960", Box 22, folder 459
    - Doets, H. C., 1962–1964 (Box 3, Folder 63)
      Incoming letters, with one outgoing letter. Enclosed in letter dated 1963 March 17 is a typed draft of Doets' text "Contribution très petite à une interprétation du tarot selon les principes de la 'pataphysique pour les besoins des jeux situationnistes."
      See also: Series II. The Situationist Times Records. Doets, H.C. "Extract of literature found on the subject of 'An Egyptian Tarot'", Box 14, folder 348
    - Douwes Dekker, Mrs., 1966 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - "E" general, 1962–1969 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Elzenga, Hans, 1963–1964 (Box 3, Folder 66)
      For outgoing correspondence possibly addressed to Elzenga, see also: First name only, Hans, Box 10, folder 266
    - Emmerich, David Georges, 1964–1976 (Box 3, Folder 67-68)
    - "F" general, 1962–1968 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Fazakerley, Gordon, 1962–1967 (Box 3, Folder 70-75)
      Incoming and outgoing correspondence with Fazakerley, some jointly with his wife Ulla Borchsensius, discussing The Situationist Times; Kazakerley's move to Denmark; his association with Danish situationists, in particular conflicts with Jens Jørgen Thorsen; exhibitions; and personal matters.
    - Fischer, Lothar, 1962–1963 (Box 3, Folder 76)
      Incoming letters from the German sculptor and member of Gruppe SPUR.
    - Fischer, Rita and Ernst, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 77-78)
    - Franceschi, G. (Gérard), 1963–1965 (Box 3, Folder 79-80)
    - [Fröhlich], Fanchon, 1962–1968 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - "G" general, 1961–1970 (Box 3, Folder 82-84)
      Includes single letters from various art galleries and receipts of payment for works by de Jong, including the purchase of posters created in the wake of the 1968 protests by Galerie du Dragon (Paris, France).
    - Galerie Birch (Copenhagen, Denmark) / Birch, Børge, 1962–1965 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Galerie Delta (Rotterdam, Netherlands) / Sonnenberg, Hans, 1962–1964 (Box 3, Folder 86-87)
      Mostly incoming letters from 1962, when Galerie Delta hosted de Jong's first solo show.
      For letters possibly addressed to Hans Sonnenberg, see also: First name only, Hans, Box 10, folder 266
    - Galerie Moderne (Silkeborg, Denmark) / Omme, Willy, 1962–1965 (Box 4, Folder 88-89)
      Most incoming and outgoing correspondence relates to de Jong's 1963 show at the gallery, including an inventory of artworks shipped to the gallery.
    - Galerie Tardy (Enschede, Netherlands) / Tardy, Léon, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Galerie van de Loo (Munich, Germany) / Loo, Otto van de, 1963–1968 (Box 4, Folder 91-92)
    - Galerie Westing (Odense, Denmark) / Derviniotis, Theo, 1963–1965 (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Garston, Jill (née Kleeman), 1961–1962 (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Gasché, Rodolphe, 1962–1964 (Box 4, Folder 95)
      See also: Series II. The Situationist Times Records, "Documents relating to the initial period of The Situationist Times", Box 19, folder 434
    - Glob, P. V. (Peter Vilhelm), 1963–1964 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Gruppe SPUR, undated (Box 4, Folder 97)
      Outgoing letters simply addressed to "SPUR".
    - "H" general, 1962–1970 (Box 4, Folder 98-100)
    - Haacke, Hans and Linda, 1961–1970 (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Hagen, Anne, 1962–1964 (Box 4, Folder 102)
      Accompanied by a letter signed "Büdi", possibly Louis Hagen Jr.
    - Hasenfratz, Doris, 1965–1969 (Box 4, Folder 103-104)
    - Hay, George, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 105)
      Includes a typescript of Hay's text "The man from inner space."
    - Henry, Maurice, 1965–1968 (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Hofman, Henk, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Holmefjord, Ingvald, 1969 and undated (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Hoopen, Peter ten, 1966–1967 (Box 4, Folder 109)
      For letters possibly addressed to Peter ten Hoopen, see also: First name only, Peter, Box 10, folder 268
    - Housden, Brian, undated (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Hovdenakk, Per, 1967–1972 (Box 4, Folder 111-113)
    - Hune (Gallery), 1967–1969 (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Imprimerie Clot, Bramsen et Georges, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - [Iersel?], Kees Van, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 116)
      Letters discussing The Situationist Times, signed by or addressed to "Kees", possibly the Dutch theater actor and director who contributed to issue no. 4.
    - "J" general, 1966–1972 (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Jaffé, Hans Ludwig C., 1961–1969 (Box 4, Folder 118-119)
      For letters possibly addressed to Hans Ludwig C. Jaffé, see also: First name only, Hans, Box 10, folder 266
    - Jònsdáttir, Selma, 1967–1968 (Box 5, Folder 120)
      Incoming letters related to Listasafn Íslands (National Gallery of Iceland).
    - Jorn, Asger
      - Letters, 1959–1970 (Box 5, Folder 121-141)
        Largely incoming letters, postcards, and telegrams, discussing Jorn's art and writing, personal life, and relationship with de Jong. Accompanied by a handful of undated outgoing letters and third-party letters.
        - Oversize letters (Box 25, Folder 490-492)
      - Short notes and travel ephemera, 1961–1967 (Box 6, Folder 142-145)
    - "K" general, 1961–1970 (Box 6, Folder 146-147)
    - Karbo, Bjørn, 1965–1967 (Box 6, Folder 148)
    - Kenedy, R. C., 1967–1975 (Box 6, Folder 149)
      Affiliated with the Victoria & Albert Museum.
    - Krikhaar, Herman, 1965–1968 (Box 6, Folder 150-151)
    - Kumar, Ashok, 1968–1969 (Box 6, Folder 152)
    - Kunzelmann, Dieter, 1961–1965 (Box 6, Folder 153-154)
      Incoming and outgoing correspondence with the German political activist and member of Gruppe SPUR.
    - "L" general, 1961–1969 (Box 6, Folder 155-156)
    - Lahumière, Anne, 1968–1970 (Box 6, Folder 157-158)
      Comprises an original grouping of letters from various individuals, mainly Lahumière, regarding the planning of the Biennale internationale de l'estampe, and outgoing letters to Lahumière, the owner of Gallerie Lahumière.
    - Lefebre, John, 1961–1969 (Box 6, Folder 159-160)
    - Leroux, M., 1961–1970 (Box 6, Folder 161-163)
      Correspondence with de Jong's landlord in Paris, including a copy of her lease dated 1961.
    - Lussanet, Paul and Geesje de, 1964–1969 (Box 7, Folder 164-165)
      - Accompanying clippings (Box 25, Folder 493)
    - "M" general, 1962–1969 (Box 7, Folder 166)
    - Marinotti, [Paolo], 1965 (Box 7, Folder 167)
    - Mayer, Peter, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 168)
      Incoming and outgoing correspondence regarding a possible contribution to The Situationist Times no. 7.
      See also: Series II. The Situationist Times Records, "Peter Mayer Practical Chemistry", Box 17, folders 404-407.
      - Restricted fragile photostats, 1967-1968 (Box 31, Folder 516)
    - Meter-Plaut, Elisabeth, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 169)
    - "N" general, 1963–1970 (Box 7, Folder 170)
    - Nash, Jørgen
      - Letters, 1962–1964 (Box 7, Folder 171-172)
        Outgoing and incoming correspondence with Nash, a Danish artist and brother of Asger Jorn, discussing the Scandinavian section of the Internationale Situationniste, Guy Debord, and The Situationist Times. Nash was associated with Bauhaus Situationniste, the artists' commune Drakabygget, and CoBrA. Includes a 1964 letter co-signed by Jens Jørgen Thorsen criticizing de Jong's work. Accompanied by related flyers, and a typescript of the manifesto "The struggle for a situcratic society", translated in English from the Danish original.
        See also: Thorsen, Jens Jørgen, Box 9, folder 239
      - Accompanying posters (Box 25, Folder 494)
    - Neuburg-Coray, Trudi, 1962–1969 (Box 7, Folder 173)
      Owner of Galleria Castelnuovo (Ascona, Switzerland)
    - "O" general, 1963–1967 (Box 7, Folder 174)
    - "P" general, 1963–1968 (Box 7, Folder 175-176)
    - Pessin, Marc, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 177)
    - Petersen, Ad, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 178)
    - Petersen, Erik, 1964–1971, undated (Box 7, Folder 179-180)
      Owner of Galerie Gammel Strand (Copenhagen, Denmark). Most incoming letters are undated.
    - Prem, Heimrad
      - Letters, 1960–1969 (Box 7, Folder 181)
        Incoming letters from 1960-1962, accompanied by typed minutes of a meeting in Munich launching "Omnibus News" dated 1969 April 16.
      - Accompanying poster (Box 25, Folder 495)
    - "R" general, 1964–1968 (Box 7, Folder 182)
    - Rap, Thomas, 1965–1968 (Box 7, Folder 183-184)
      Largely incoming letters from the Dutch publisher, who helped distribute The Situationist Times, accompanied by a promotional brochure for "Thomas Rap, Uitgever."
    - Reichardt, Jasia, 1962–1975 (Box 7, Folder 185)
      Assistant director of the Institute of Contemporary Arts, London, and director of Whitechapel Art Gallery.
    - Remfeldt, Per, 1968–1969 (Box 7, Folder 186-187)